(+34) 691-752-157 Madrid, Spain jiangwenqi1995@gmail.com

Wenqi Jiang

Data Engineer

jiangwenqi.info github.com/jiangwenqi linkedin.com/in/jiangwenqi

Having nearly 5 years of experience as a software engineer in big data infrastructure and backend services, mainly focused on specializing in scalability, high availability, and low latency distributed systems design and implementation. Proficient in Java.

WORKING EXPERIENCE

${\bf Software\ Engineer\ (Scholarship)\ |\ OEG\text{-}UPM}$

Feb. 2022 - Jul. 2022

Madrid, Spain

- Analyzed ontologies from different graph data sources, like DBpedia, Wikidata;
- Specialized 7 linking discovery algorithms, including string-based similarity and geometry relationships;
- Implemented a SPARQL-based linking application by using Apache Jena, and evaluated it with the OAEI-2021 datasets;
- · Written the master's thesis.

Big Data Engineer | TOGIC Offline Data Warehouse

May 2019 - Aug. 2021

Shenzhen, China

- Maintained the Hadoop cluster containing over 200 TB of data, including user and system logs from 3 different sources;
- Upgraded big data components, like Hadoop, Spark, Kafka, etc., and monitored them on CDH;
- Designed and implemented a four-layer data warehouse based on the STAR model by using Hive, which had near 150 tables and received over 300 GB per day;
- Rewrote the ETL pipeline, which saved over 80% of storage and fixed the small files' problem on HDFS.

Data Statistics System

- Restructured the statistics system based on the new offline data warehouse;
- Rewrote the code by using Spark DSL, making it more readable and maintainable;
- Optimized the system's performance, reduced the process time by 25% compared to the previous version;
- Implemented more than 30 new statistical demands and fixed bugs.

Log Collection Service

- Designed and implemented the log collection pipeline using Nginx and Netty, improving performance, stability, and scalability;
- Processed all logs into the Kafka cluster, which has 5 brokers, 3 replications, and 7 days of redundancy, improving robustness.

Backend Engineer | WEBSTUDIO

Jul. 2018 - Apr. 2019

- Implemented backend APIs of big data visualization dashboards and general reports for the BI applications;
 - Beijing, China

- Implemented the one-click function of syncing all user information;
- Expanded 16 data sources, including MySQL, SQL Server, MongoDB etc.;
- Maintained the big data cluster, fixed bugs and developed new features for the previous projects.

Developed more than 25 data operators, such as summation, date conversion, string processing etc.;

Software Engineering Intern | KEG-THU

Nov. 2017 - Jun. 2018

- Annotated critical illness insurance documents, and maintained the NoSQL databases: MongoDB and Neo4i;
 Beijing, China
- Trained models to extract the logical structure of insurance documents by using GROBID;
- Created a desktop application for applying the models;
- Completed the bachelor's thesis.

OPEN SOURCE CONTRIBUTIONS

Dapp Learning DAO Apr. 2022 - Present

- Contributed and translated various tutorial tasks;
- Shared the latest blockchain news and cutting-edge technics in the community.

EDUCATION

MS. Data Science · Polytechnic University of Madrid	2021 - 2022
BE. Computer Science and Technology · Beijing Information Science & Technology University	2014 - 2018

SKILLS

TechniquesJava, Scala, Hadoop, Kafka, Hive, HBase, CDH, Spark, Flink
Python, Elasticsearch, MySQL, MongoDB, Docker

Languages English (B2), Mandarin (Native)